THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
字幕：破烂熊
校对、调轴、格式化：Obster-Y@github
仅供交流  严禁商用
正式访问
“尽管1978年苏格兰法案A节第3小节
"Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection 3, section A,
第二百一十四条对此有所规定
clause 214 of the Administrative Procedures Scotland Act 1978,
仍然建议
it is proposed that in so far as
就法律条文的执行而言
the implementation of the statutory provisions is concerned,
各责任部门间非正常的
the resolution of anomalies and uncertainties
和不确定的情况
as between responsible departments
属于行政部
shall fall within the purview of
大臣权限之内”
the Minister for Administrative Affairs".
什么意思?
What does it mean?
-对不起?  -这是什么意思?
- I'm sorry? - What does it mean?
哦...是这样 大臣
Oh, er, well, Minister,
意思是“尽管法案有所规定...”
it means "notwithstanding the provisions of..."
别读给我听 我刚读过 到底是什么意思?
Don't read it to me. I've just read it to you. What does it mean?
就是它说的那意思 大臣
What it says, Minister.
请允许我提醒您 大臣
May I remind you, Minister.
还有15分钟您要接见劳工代表团
you are seeing a deputation from the TUC in 15 minutes,
之后过半小时是全国工联代表
from the CBI half an hour after that,
中午12点是企业局代表
and from the NEB at 12 noon.
-他们来想要什么?  -都担心机器设备的事
- What do they all want? - They're all worried about machinery.
-机器?  -是的 担心会通胀、紧缩、以及再通胀
- Machinery? - Yes, for inflation, deflation and reflation.
他们当我是什么
What do they think I am,
一个内阁大臣 还是自行车打气筒?
a Minister of the Crown or a bicycle pump?
我什么时候才有时间答复这些信件?
When am I going to do all this correspondence?
您得知道 其实不用回 大臣
You do realise you don't actually have to, Minister.
-不用吗?  -要是不想回就不用回
- Don't I? - Not if you don't want to.
可以草拟一份官方回复
We can draft an official reply.
官方答复是什么意思?
What's the official reply?
就是回复“大臣感谢你的来信”
It just says "The Minister thanks you for the letter".
再说些“正在考虑当中” 类的话
Then we say something like "The matter is under consideration".
要是您觉得一样 也可以说 “正在积极考虑当中”
Or even, if you feel the same "under active consideration".
有何不同?
What's the difference?
“在考虑当中”意思是文件已经丢了
"Under consideration" means we've lost the file,
“在积极考虑当中”的意思是我们正在找
"Under active consideration" means we're trying to find it.
您只要把信件移到这边的文件格
You just transfer all the letters to your Out Tray,
要是您想看到回复就在边上加批注
put a brief note on the margin if you wish to see the reply
如果不加 就再也不用去管它了
and if you don't, you never see or hear of it again.
把东西从这里移到这里 不用去看
If I transfer everything from here to here, without even reading it,
-我要做的就是这样  -是的
- That's all I have to do? - Yes.
-会有人来处理?  -没错
- It will be dealtwith? - Precisely.
-处理完毕?  -毫无纰漏
- Properly? - Immaculately.
那大臣是来干什么的?
What's the Minister here for then?
呃... 来决定政策 大臣
Er... to make policy decisions, Minister.
当您已经决定政策 我们会来执行
When you've decided the policy, we can carry it out.
需要经常决定政策吗?
How often are policy decisions needed?
有时候需要
From time to time.
Bernard，这届政府是来管理国家的
Bernard, this government is here to govern.
不能像往届那样就是来统治
Not merely preside like our predecessors did.
当一个国家正在走下坡路时
When a country is going downhill,
得有人坐在驾驶席上
it's time for someone to get into the driving seat,
往油门上踩一脚
put his foot on the accelerator.
我想您是指刹车吧
I think you mean the brake.
-呃 Humphrey  -打扰一会儿 大臣
- Ah, Humphrey. - A moment of your time, Minister.
“Buranda国总统对英国的正式访问”
"The official visit to the UK of the President of Buranda".
Buranda在哪儿?
Where's Buranda?
-非洲  -从没听过
- Africa. - I've never heard of it.
是的 大臣 一个很新的国家
Yes, it's fairly new, Minister.
以前叫做英属赤道非洲
It used to be called British Equatorial Africa.
就是左手边的那个红点 在地中海下面(指地图上)
It's the red bit on the left hand side, below the Mediterranean.
哦 是那儿 为什么交给我?
Oh, there! But why's this come to us?
这是外交部的事
This is for the Foreign Office.
不 不全是 有些行政问题
No. Not exactly. There are administrative problems.
女王陛下在Balmoral宫
Her Majesty's due to be up at Balmoral at the time,
所以要来伦敦
so she'll have to come to London.
国家访问不是几年前就定下来了吗
I thought state visits are arranged years in advance.
这不是国家访问 而是政府首脑访问
This isn't a state visit, it's a Head of Government visit.
Buranda总统不就是国家首领
Usually the President of Buranda is Head of State.
但他也是政府首脑 大臣
But he's also Head of Government, Minister
如果他作为政府首脑而来
But if he's coming as Head of Government,
还要女王见他干吗?
why does the Queen have to see him?
因为他是国家首领 大臣
Because she's the Head of State, Minister.
国家首领来访必须由国家首领来迎接
The Head of State must greet a Head of State,
就算那人不是以国家首领的身份而来
even if he's not here as Head of State.
这都是戴帽子的问题 大臣
It's all a matter of hats, Minister
帽子?
Hats?
是的 他戴着一顶政府首脑的帽子来访
Yes. He's coming wearing his Head of Government hat.
他也是国家首领 但不能算是国家访问
He is the Head of State, too, but it's not a state visit
因为他没戴那顶国家首领的帽子
because he's not wearing his Head of State hat,
但外交礼节要求
but protocol demands
就算他戴着一顶政府首脑的帽子
even though he's wearing his Head of Government hat,
仍必须由女王来迎接他
he must still be met by the Crown.
为什么我们要接受
Why are we having an official visit from
-这个非洲弹丸小国的来访?  -大臣阁下
- this tin pot little African country? - Minister,
我请求您别管它叫做非洲弹丸小国
I beg of you not to referto it as a tin pot little African country.
-这是个L.D.C  -什么?
- It's an L.D.C. - What?
Buranda就是以前所谓的不发达国家
Buranda is what used to be called an Under-developed Country.
然而 这种叫法被普遍认为有失礼貌
However, this term was widely regarded as offensive...
于是他们被称作发展中国家
so they became known as Developing Countries
又叫作欠发达国家 即L.D.C.
and then as Less Developed Countries or L.D.C.'s.
现在我们准备把L.D.C这个称呼换成H.R.R.C.
We are now ready to replace the term L.D.C. with H.R.R.C.
那又是什么?
What's that?
-人力资源丰富的国家  -意思是?
- Human Resource Rich Countries. - Which means?
他们人口严重过剩 是来要钱的
They're grossly overpopulated and begging for money.
Buranda就是个H.R.R.C?
And Buranda is an H.R.R.C?
不 大臣
No, Minister.
别这么严谨 这算是个富国还是个穷国?
Don't be that strict. Is it one of the "have" or "have not" countries?
我们也不再用这种称呼了
We don't use that term any longer.
但是非要这么说的话 Buranda是个“将会富”的国家
But if we did, Buranda would be a "will have" nation.
将会富?
Will have?
两三年后 将会富有大量石油
Will have a huge amount of oil in a couple of years from now.
哦 我明白了
Oh, I see.
干吗不早说啊?
Why didn't you say so at first?
-它根本不是个T.P.L.A.C.  -T.P.L.A.C?
- It's not a T.P.L.A.C. At all. - T.P.L.A.C?
非洲弹丸小国
Tin Pot Little African Country.
绝不是 大臣
No, Minister.
石油 等等 我有个绝妙的注意
Oil. Wait for a moment. I've got a marvellous idea.
女王根本不用从Balmoral宫赶到这儿来
The Queen doesn't have to come down from Balmoral.
您是否建议 让女王陛下和那位总统
Are you proposing that Her Majesty and the president should exchange
通过电话互致正式问候?
official greetings over the telephone?
不 不 不 不
No. No. No. No.
难道您是要他们大声呼喊?
that perhaps you'd like them to shout rather loudly?
不是 访问应该在苏格兰进行
No. The visit shall take place in Scotland.
-在Holyrood宫  -不可能
- At Holyrood Palace. - Out of the question.
-为什么?  -这不由我们决定
- Why? - It's not our decision.
-这是外交部的事  -不是吧
- It's a Foreign Office matter. - I don't think so.
“尽管法案有所规定...
"Notwithstanding the provisions of subsection 3 blah blah...
仍然建议...
it is proposed blah...
各责任部门间非正常的和...
the resolution of anomalies and uncertainties blah...
属于行政部
shall fall within the purview
-大臣权限之内”  -哦 是的 不过…
- of the Minister for Administrative Affairs." - Oh, yes but…
还不明白? 多棒的主意
Don't you see? It's brilliant.
我们让女王免去了一趟毫无意义的行程
We save the Queen a pointless journey,
正好苏格兰要举行三场补缺选举
and there are three Scottish by-elections coming up soon
都是边缘选区
everyone of the marginal.
访问一结束就举行
We'll hold them straight after the visit.
大臣阁下 我们不能因为党派政治而
Minister, we do not hold Head of Government visits
举行政府首脑访问  我们是为了国家
for party political reasons, but for reasons of State.
可我的计划正表明苏格兰是英国地位平等的一部分
My plan shows that Scotland is an equal partner in the UK.
她也是苏格兰女王 这你明白
She is Queen of Scotland too. You Know.
而苏格兰有很多边缘选...我是说 经济萧条地区
And it is full of marginal constit... I mean depressed areas.
大臣阁下 我可不认为利用王室
Minister, I hardly think that we can exploit our Sovereign
就意味着要把女王卷入到所谓的
by involving her in what some might call
肮脏的拉票活动中
a squalid vote grubbing exercise.
-你需要更好的理由?  -的确需要
- You want a better reason, right? - Indeed we do.
那你告诉我他为何而来
Then tell me why he's coming.
来就共同利益交换意见
For exchange of views on matters of mutual interest.
-告诉我他是为何而来  -近海石油钻井设备
- Now tell me why he's coming. - Off shore drilling equipment.
希望他会和英国政府签一笔大单子
We're hoping he's going to place a huge order with BG.
他要上哪儿去看这些设备?
And where is he going to see all this off shore equipment?
-Aberdeen、Clydeside  -没错
- Aberdeen. Clydeside. - Yes.
你在Haslemere镇有多少钻塔 Humphrey?
How many oil rigs have you got in Haslemere?
但是行政上的问题…
But the administrative problems…
本部门就是为解决行政问题而建立的
That's what this whole department was created to solve.
-可苏格兰太远了  -也没多远
- But Scotland's so remote. - Not all that remote.
就是Potter's Bar镇上面两英寸粉红色的那小块
It's that pink bit about two feet above Potter's Bar.
这真有趣 大臣
Very droll, Minister.
好了 就在苏格兰了
So, it's going to be Scotland.
这就是我决定的政策
That is my policy decision.
我就是来干这个的 是吗 Bernard?
That's what I'm here for, right Bernard?
是吗 Humphrey? 很好 谢谢
Right Humphrey? Good, thank you.
他为什么反对这个主意 Bernad? 我是说 真实原因
What's he got against the idea Bernad? I mean realy.
Humphrey爵士很喜欢参加大使馆的宴会
Well, Sir Humphrey likes going to Foreign Embassies,
打着白领结 身穿燕尾服 胸别勋章 衣冠楚楚
with his white tie, tails, medals.
要是在苏格兰 场面就小多了
It will all be on a much smaller scale of expectation in Scotland.
你是说 Humphrey露面的机会不多?
You mean no room for Humphrey?
基本上没有 只有苏格兰的常任秘书才有机会
Probably not. Only for the Permanent Secretary of Scottish Office.
Humphrey爵士有很多...吗?
Has Sir Humphrey got lots of um...?
有 大臣 一两枚吧
Yes one or two, Minister.
他还被推荐为下届高级英帝国勋爵
He's been recommended for the KBE in the next honours list.
你怎么知道的?
How do you know?
我以为授勋的事一直是严格保密的
I thought honours were a closely guarded secret.
-再来点咖啡吗 巨人?  -谢谢 小汉
- More coffee, Jumbo? - Thank you, Humpy.
外交大臣不会同意了这个荒谬的
Any luck with the Foreign Secretary about this
苏格兰方案吧?
Scottish nonsense?
恐怕是的 说不动他 你的大臣先把他拉拢了
Afraid not. Can't budge him. Your Minister nobbled him first.
不可能再弄回伦敦了?
No chance of getting it back to London?
不可能了 看来内阁是完全一致
No, I'm afraid the Cabinet are utterly united.
都是为了边缘地区的选票 看出来了吧?
All these marginal seats, d'you see?
真不要脸
Shameful.
党派政治
Political.
太典型了
Typical.
无法避免
Inevitable.
还这么招摇
And so blatant.
我是说 公然颁布了在访问之后
I mean issuing writs for three Scottish by-elections
举行三场补缺选举的文件
to poll on the day after the visit.
你能想像Harold·MacMillan(首相)会做出这种事吗?
Can you imagine Harold MacMillan doing a thing like that?
能
Yes.
是啊 其实我也认为会
Yes, so can I, actually.
那么 苏格兰那边的安排
Now, about the arrangements for Scotland.
我是说接待 你知道谁会去吗?
The reception I mean. Do we know who's going?
是啊 Buranda在爱丁堡的领事馆
Yes. I'm afraid the Burandan Consulate in Edinburgh
恐怕就是个猪圈
is rather a hutch.
还不又得让我一个人
I shall have to carry the flag
为了这些行政事务忙前忙后
for the Civil Service all by myself.
是吗?
Oh really?
真同情你
Well, you have my sympathy.
天知道他们会给
God knows what they'll be
那些苏格兰人和Buranda人吃些什么
serving up for the Scots and Burandans.
教会调料拌苏格兰羊杂 除了这个还会是什么
Haggis in missionary sauce, I shouldn't wonder.
私下里说 其实很可能不会有什么访问了
Actually, between ourselves, the visit will probably never happen.
-不会有? 为什么?  -内部不太平
- Never happen? Why? - Rumblings in the interior.
哦 天哪… 哦 我明白了
Oh dear... Oh, I see what you mean.
-我们驻Mungoville的人这么说的  -有那么严重吗?
- From our man in Mungoville. - Isn't that rather serious?
Buranda是个友好的非洲国家
Buranda's a friendly African country
也算是英联邦的友邦
with a Common Wealth connection.
我们的情报是它可能会变成一个敌对的
Our information is it's likely to turn into a hostile L.D.C.
跟古巴搭上关系的欠发达国家
With a Cuban connection.
-政府会怎么做?  -就和以往一样...
- What will the Government do? - The same as always...
管他呢!
Damn all!
(BBC 电视新闻)
刚刚收到报导 西非国家Buranda
We are just getting reports of a coup d'etat in Buranda,
也就是前英属赤道非洲发生了政变
the West African State, formerly British Equatorial Africa.
早先的报导说总司令
Earlier report suggested that the Commander in Chief
Selim·Mohammed宣布成为该国总统
Colonel Selim Mohammed has been declared President.
前总统Alam情况不明
It is not known what's happened to President Alam,
而后者原定于下周对英国进行正式访问
who was due to pay an official visit to Britain next week.
还没有迹象表明...
There is still no sign of agreement...
看到了吗? 快给我接外交大臣
Did you see that? Get me the Foreign Secretary.
要封锁消息吗?
Shall we scramble?
封锁 不 已经不是秘密了 都成新闻了
Scramble. No, it's not secret, it's on the news.
Martin
Martin.
-Buranda这事怎么办?  -怎么回事?
- What's all this about Buranda? - What's all what?
那里发生政变了
There's been a coup d'etat.
你怎么知道的?
How do you know?
都上电视了 你没看到吗?
It was on the news. Didn't you see?
你不知道? 你可是外交大臣啊! 天哪
Don't you know? You're Foreign Secretary! For god's sake.
是啊 可我的电视机出毛病了
Yes. But my TV set's on the blink.
你的电视机? 你不是有外交部电文么?
Your TV set? Don't you get foreign office telegrams?
不 电文总是晚到 我都从电视上看国际新闻的
No, they always come in later. I get all the foreign news from TV.
-你在开玩笑...对吧?  -不开玩笑
- You're joking... aren't you? - No.
正式访问怎么办?
What about this official visit?
-必须保证访问照常进行 对吗?  -我们能怎么办?
- We've got to make sure this still happens. - How can we?
-新总统是谁?  -得查清楚
- Who's the new President? - We must find out.
确保他会来 管他是谁
And make sure he comes. whoever he is.
-还有三场补缺选举靠这个呢  -这我知道
- There are three by-elections hanging on it. - I know that.
一有进一步消息就告诉我
Let me know if you hear anything more...
不 还是你告诉我 你有电视
No, you let me know. You're the one with the telly.
-听到那个坏消息了吗 大臣阁下?  -是啊 简直是灾难
- You've heard the sad news? - Yes, disaster.
不 不 不 不 只是小小的不便
No. No. No. No, just a slight inconvenience.
轮子已经转起来了 取消访问
The wheels are in motion. Now it's really perfectly simple
不过是件简单的事情
to cancel the arrangements for the visit.
取消访问? 你不能这么做
Cancel the visit? You'll do no such thing.
我们别无选择 大臣
We have no choice, Minister.
我刚和外交大臣谈过
I've just been speaking with the Foreign Secretary.
我们将重新邀请新总统访问
We are reissuing the invitation for the new President.
可是 我们还没承认他的政府
But, we haven't recognised his government.
轮子已经开始转了
The wheels are in motion.
-可新总统是谁?  -Mohammed什么的
- But who is he? - Mohammed something.
我们对他一无所知 他到底是什么样的人?
We know nothing about him. What's he like?
Humphrey，他是来访问的
Humphrey, he's coming here on a official visit.
我们又不是让他加入国会俱乐部
We're not putting him up after the Athenaeum.
大臣阁下
Minister.
Buranda还处于混乱之中
Buranda is in total confusion.
我们不知道谁在为他撑腰
We don't know who is behind him.
我们不知道他是仗着苏联而来
We don't know Whether he's Soviet backed,
还是个只为了敲竹杠而来的普通Buranda人
or just a ordinary Burandan with an eye for the main chance.
我们不能冒外交风险
We cannot take diplomatic risks.
-政府别无选择  -可是女王陛下...
- The Government has no choice. - But Her Majesty...
女王陛下能够应付 她总能应付
Her Majesty will cope. She always does.
但那人到底是谁?
But who is he?
他可能很没教养
He might not be properly brought up.
他可能对她言行粗鲁
He might be rude to her.
他可能会对女王动手动脚
He might take liberties.
他肯定会跟女王合影
He will be photographed with Her Majesty
那时发现他是又一个ldi·Amin(乌干达暴君)怎么办?
and what if he turns out to be another ldi Amin.
这样的后果将可怕得难以预料
The repercussions are too hideous to contemplate.
-我们会查清楚他  -我们办不到
- We'll find out about him. - We can't.
在我们眼里他仍是一个谜团
All that we know is that he's an enigma.
Humphrey，我不喜欢这个词
Humphrey, I don't care for that word.
谜团?
Enigma?
国家的大计使这次访问成为必然
And there are reasons of State which make this visit essential.
Buranda资源丰富充满前景
Buranda is potentially and enormously rich.
他们需要钻塔 而我们在Clyde河边的船厂却闲着
It needs oil rigs and we have idle shipyards on the Clyde.
此外 Buranda是我们非洲政策不可或缺的一部分
Moreover, Buranda is essential to our African policy.
政府没有非洲政策
The Government doesn't have an African policy.
那么 现在有了
Well, it has now.
要是真有共产党给他撑腰
And if it is Marxist backed,
谁比女王陛下更合适把他拉拢过来?
who better to win him over to our side than her Majesty?
况且我们已经答应了苏格兰人民
Moreover, the people of Scotland has been promised
将在那里举行这次国事活动 我们不能食言
the important state occassion can not go back on ours words.
更不用说为了边缘地区的三次补缺选举
Not to mention three marginal by-elections.
更不用说那三次...这可与此无关
Not to mention... Which has nothing whatever to do with it!
当然没有
No, Of course not, Minister.
请说? 是外交大臣
Yes? It's the Foreign Secretary.
Martin? 好 好
Martin? Yes Yes.
访问将如期进行
The visit's on.
哦 太好了
Oh, splendid.
Buranda的新总统已宣布有意
The new President of Buranda has announced his intention
于下周访问英国
to visiting this country next week,
和他前任的安排一致
in accordance with his predecessor's arrangements.
看来 外交部终于得到了确定的事实
So, the Foreign Office is getting the facts at last?
其实 也不全是
Well, not exactly.
是Martin的司机从汽车收音机里听到的简讯
Martin's driver heard a newsflash on his car radio.
好了 访问将如期进行
So, the visit's on.
这就是我给首相的提议
That is my recommendation to the PM.
又一项政策决定 Bernard
Another policy decision, Bernard.
还真做了不少决策了呢 是吗?
Quite a lot of them after all, aren't they?
Buranda航空 还真行啊
Burandan Airways! They are doing well.
-他们有多少飞机?  - 一架也没有
- How many planes do they got? - None.
别犯傻了 那这架呢?
You derisible, What about that one?
这架是上周刚从Freddie·Laker航空公司那租来的
That one was chartered from Freddie Laker last week
特地重新刷过了
and repainted specially.
实际上 曾有一架747飞机在一个月内
Actually, there's one 747 that belonged to
曾归属于9家不同的非洲航空公司
9 different African airlines in one month.
他们称之为“非洲之神”
They called it the Mumbo Jumbo.
-我的飞机是几点的?  -我给您订了火车卧铺
- When do I have to be in the Heathrow? - Oh I've booked you on the sleeper, Minister.
-您今晚还得去下院  -哦 上帝
- You'll be at the House tonight. - Oh, lord.
现在我们将一睹
And now we are about to catch our first glimpse
Buranda总统Selim·Mohammed的风采
of President Selim Mohammed of Buranda.
我认识他! 是Charlie
I know him! That's Charlie.
-Charlie?  -我们是伦敦政治经济学院的同学
- Charlie? - We were at L.S.E. Together.
他不是什么Selim·Mohammed 他是Charles·Umtali
He's not Selim Mohammed, he's Charles Umtali.
你确信?
Are you sure?
Charles·Umtali这样的名字可不容易忘掉
You don't forget a name like Charlie Umtali.
还有什么资料吗 Bernard?
Have we anything on this, Bernard?
我查了简介 Humphrey爵士
In the brief it stated
上面说Selim·Mohammed上校
that Colonel Selim Mohammed
几年前入了伊斯兰教
was converted to Islam some years ago.
查不到他原先叫什么
We didn't know his previous name,
更别说什么背景了
so we couldn't find out much about his background.
这我倒知道 这家伙是个激进的政治经济学家
Well I can tell you all about him. He's a red hot political economist.
总是先发制人 战胜每个对手
Got the door first, wiped the floor with everyone.
-那就好了  -什么意思?
- Well, That's all right then. - Is it why?
我想Bernard的意思是他既然上过英国的大学
What I think what Bernard means is that
就该知道检点自己的行为
you know how to behave when you went to an English University.
就算是在伦敦政经学院
Even if it was the L.S.E.
你说这人很激进 是指政治上吗?
You said red hot, were you speaking politically?
某种程度上是 跟Charlie在一起会让你迷失方向
Partly. You never quite know where you're with Charlie.
他是那种跟着你进旋转门
He's sort of person who follows you into a revolving door
出来的时候却在你前面
and comes out first.
没什么很深的信仰吧?
No deep commitment?
-只对他自己  -我明白了 是个政客 大臣
- Only to Charlie. - I see. A politician, Minister.
很有趣 Humphrey
Very droll, Humphrey.
就待几天 不会有问题
It'll be a couple of days. Can't do much harm.
请千万记住 大臣 是你要他来的 不是我
Always remember, Minister, you wanted him here, not me.
列车半小时后出发 大臣
It is after half past, Minister.
什么时候才能处理这些信件?
When am I going to do all this correspondence?
其实 大臣...
Well, Minister...
干得好 大臣 送出去总比收进来好
Well done, Minister. Better out than in.
十点三十分开往爱丁堡的列车
22:30 Edinburgh train
将从七号站台发车
will leave from Platform 7...
-谁?  -Bernard
- Who is it? - Bernard.
进来 Bernard 什么事?
Come in. Bernard, what's the matter?
-您看一下这个好吗?  -不 我不看
- Would you read this, please? - No, I will not.
-可情况紧急  -什么事你都这么说
- But it's top priority. - You always say like that at about everything.
这是Selim总统明天演讲稿的复印件
This is an advanced copy of President Selim's speech tomorrow.
我们刚从Buranda大使馆拿到
We just got it from the Brianda Embassy
我了解这种演讲
I know about these speeches:
很高兴来到贵国 什么互相交流的重要性啊
Happy to be here, bonds of shared experience,
两国间的联系啊 是这样吗?
Ties between our two countries, am I right?
是的 里面都写了 可是...
Oh, yes. That is all in it, but...
我今晚可不会看这个
I'm certainly not going to read it tonight.
大臣 我真觉得您该看一下
I really think you should, Minister..
重点我已经用红笔划出来了
I've underlined the important bits in red ink.
我再到其他车厢发几份
I'll just distribute some copies around the train.
其他车厢?
Around the train?
是的 Humphrey爵士 外交大臣
Yes. To Sir Humphrey, the Foreign Secretary,
新闻官都在列车上
the Press Officer all on the train...
“Buranda人民感到自己
"Burandans feel
和他们的共同战友…
a special affinity with the…
所有凯尔特人后代
Celtic peoples
在争取民族自由的斗争中有着共鸣
in their struggle for freedom.
我们都面临着为摆脱
We too had to fight to break free
英殖民主义而战的艰巨任务”
from the chains of British colonialism".
英殖民主义?
Bristish colonialism?
“Buranda人民催促苏格兰人和爱尔兰人
"The people of Buranda urge the Scots and the Irish
结束英国的压迫 摆脱帝国主义的枷锁
to end the English oppression, cast off the imperialist yoke
加入到自由国家的行列中”
and join the fellowship of free nations".
我的天!
Good God!
请进
Yes.
哦 大臣
Well, Minister.
要是被抓到不穿裤子我们就好看了
We would appear to have been caught with our trousers down.
Humphrey 他怎么能当着女王的面讲这个
Humphrey, he can't say this in front of her.
我无意冒犯 但我的确提醒过你了
I don't like to say I told you so, but I told you so.
这下脸上挂不住了
Egg all over our faces.
挂得住 大臣 只是挂得是帝国主义的“枷锁”
Not egg, Minister, just imperialist "yoke".
周四在苏格兰还有三次补缺选举
Three Scottish by-elections on Thursday.
是啊 这的确是场灾难 一场悲剧
Oh, yes. It is indeed a catastrophe. A tragedy.
震荡 天谴 空前的浩劫
A cataclysmic, apocalyptic, monumental calamity.
-是你造成的  -Humphrey 付你工资就是要你给我建议!
- And you did it. - Humphrey, you're paid to advise me, advise me!
我可不喜欢在泰坦尼克号撞上冰山后
This is not I like trying to advise the Captain of the Titanic
再给船长您提建议
after he's struck the iceberg.
必须做点什么
There must be something we can do.
我们唱“救主同住”如何?
We could sing Abide with Me?
-请进?  -大臣
- Yes? - Minister.
外交大臣要见您
The Foreign Secretary would like a word.
-外交大臣  -你看过了吗?
- Ah, Foreign Secretary. - Have you read this...?
是啊 大臣正担心政府的脸上
Yes. My Minister is concerned that our government
会被丢鸡蛋了 大概是苏格兰鸡蛋吧
will have egg all over our face. Scotch egg, presumably.
他为什么这么做?
Why is he doing it?
大概是说给国内听的 他刚当上总统
Maybe it's for home consumption. He's only just taken over.
或许他要让其他非洲国家领导人相信
Perhaps he's trying to persuade the other African Leaders
他是个真正的反殖民主义者
that he's a pukka anticolonialist.
-请进 -什么事 Bernard?
- Yes? - Yes, Bernard?
新闻官要见您
The Press Officer would like a word.
天哪!
Oh dear!
还能站进来个小个子吗?
Room for a little 'un?
Humphrey 你觉得发表声明怎么样?
Do you think it's good idea to issue a statement?
其实 大臣 具体而言
Well, Minister, in practical terms
我们有六种通常可用的选择
we have the usual six options.
其一 听之任之
One, do nothing.
其二 发表声明 对演说表示遗憾
Two, issue a statement deploring the speech.
其三 提出正式抗议
Three, lodge an official protest.
其四 停止援助
Four, cut off aid.
其五 断绝外交关系
Five, break off diplomatic relations.
-最后 宣战  -那该选哪个?
- And six, declare war. - Which should we do?
要是听之任之 就等于默认了演讲内容
If we do nothing, we implicitly agree with the speech.
第二 如果发表声明 我们就会出丑
Two, if we issue a statement, we will just look foolish.
第三 如果我们提出抗议 他们不会放在眼里
Three, if we lodge a protest, it will be ignored.
第四 我们无法停止援助 因为我们没援助过
Four, we can't cut off aid because we don't give them any.
第五 要是断绝外交关系
Five, if we break off diplomatic relations
就谈不成钻井合同了
we can't negotiate the oil rig contracts.
最后 如果向他们宣战
And six, if we declare war,
那就显得有些反应过火了
it might just look as if we were overreacting.
-要是在过去 就该派炮艇了 -是啊
- In the old days we'd just send in a gun boat. - Oh yes.
我想 这是绝对办不到的?
I suppose that IS absolutely out of the question?
-请进?  -大臣...
- Yes? - Minister...
是常务外交次长
The Permanent UnderSecretary of the Foreign Office
正沿着车厢走过来
is coming down the corridor over there
这里就要变成Calcutta的黑牢了
It'll be like the Black Hole of Calcutta.
-可以进来吗 大臣  -你试试吧
- May I come in, Minister. - You can try.
这就是我们要的一切
This is all we needed.
欢迎来到“站着的”委员会  (原意是常务委员会)
Welcome to the Standing Committee.
Frederick爵士 看过这爆炸性的演讲稿了吧?
Sir Frederick, you see this bomb-able speech?
我们该怎么办?
what are we going to do about this?
其实 大臣 外长...
Well, Minister, Foreign Secretary...
我觉得...
I think...
我觉得我们知道这是出于什么原因
I think we know what's behind it,
对吧 小汉?
don't we, Humpy?
小汉?
Humpy?
我想Frederick爵士的意思
I think Sir Frederick is suggesting
是这段讨厌的内容其实
that the offending paragraph may be
可以说 是他们讨价还价的本钱
Shall we say, a bargaining counter.
你是说他有所企图?
You mean he wants something?
否则提前把复印稿给我们干吗?
Well, if he doesn't why send us an advance copy?
明白了 那就弄清楚他想要什么?
See. Why don't you find out what it is he wants?
大使馆都是新手 我们也才刚拿到这份演说稿
The Embassy staffs are all new, we've just seen the speech.
又没有人对这位总统有所了解
And no one knows anything about this President.
除了我
Except me.
-除了你 怎么会?  -他们是大学同学
- Except you? How? - They were at a University together.
-老同学关系啊  -那是二十五年前的事了
- The old boy network. - That was 25 years ago.
他可能都不记得我了... 我觉得我真不行...
He may not even remember me... I don't really think I could...
我觉得你该去见他 Frederick
I think you ought to see him, Frederick.
不 大臣 我觉得您份量更重
No, Minister. I think you carry more weight.
那好 我们就都同意
Well, we are all agreed then
该让这座大山去见Mohammed?
that the mountain shall go to Mohammed?
不 不 不 Jim去
No. No. No. Jim's going.
我就是此意
That's what I meant.
好吧 但你得和我一块儿去
All right, but you'll have to come with me.
当然了 大臣
Of course, Minister.
我是不会让您一个人上的
I'd hardly let you do it on your own.
Jim 快进来
Oh, Jim, come in.
-真高兴能再见到你  -Charlie... 好久不见
- How nice to see you again. - Charlie... Long time no see.
你可不用跟我讲洋泾浜英语 Jim
You don't have to speak pidgin English to me, Jim
这位是我的常务次长 Humphrey·Appleby爵士
This is Sir Humphrey Appleby, my Permanent UnderSecretary.
-阁下  -你好
- Your Excellency. - How do you do.
坐吧
Do sit down.
我一直以为常务次长
I've always thought that Permanent UnderSecretary
是个低三下四的头衔
is such a demeaning title.
您说什么?
I beg your pardon?
听起来就像个助理打字员之流
Sounds like an Assistant Typist or something,
其实你掌管一切 是吗?
whereas you're really in charge of everything, aren't you?
其实 也不是一切
Well, not quite everything.
Charlie 我要祝贺你
Charlie, I suppose I should congratulate you
成为了一位国家首领
on becoming a Head of State.
谢谢 这不难
Oh, thanks. It wasn't difficult.
我用不着去做什么烦琐的事 比如竞选
I didn't have to do any of the boring things, like fighting elections
或是补缺选举之类
or by-elections.
Jim 我当然很高兴见到你
Jim, of course I'm delighted to see you,
不过你这次来只是想叙叙旧
but is this purely a social visit,
还是有什么特别的事要谈?
or is there anything in particular you wanted to talk about?
我还得花时间最后再润色一下演讲稿
Because I do have to put a finish in touches of my speech.
是的... 实际上 我们看了稿子复印件
Ah... Well, yes... Actually, we have seen an advanced copy...
喜欢吗?
You liked it?
Charlie 我就开门见山吧?
Charlie, may I speak frankly?
-我们是老朋友了 对吧?  -当然
- I mean we're old friends, aren't we? - Of course.
你一定明白那段讲殖民压迫的
You must realise that that bit about colonialist oppression
有那么一点... 非常...
was a bit... well... um, very...
其实 十分之令人尴尬
Well, actually profoundly embarrassing.
你那段催促苏格兰人和爱尔兰人...
That passage where you urged the Scots and the Irish to er...
我想是不是可以... 省略掉?
I wonder if you could um, give it a miss?
-省略掉?  -是的
- Give it a miss? - Yes.
但是 我深深地感到这是如此真实
But, this is something I feel very, very deeply to be true.
相信贵国政府不会压制真相吧?
Surely the British don't believe in suppressing the truth?
当然不会
Good heavens no.
总统阁下 我想是否有办法说服您
I wonder if there's anything that might persuade you, President.
改变一下措辞 将其重点
to consider recasting that sentence and transfering the emphasis
从具体的事例 转移到抽象的概念上去
from the specific instance to the abstract concept
当然了 不管怎样 又不至于
without, of course, in any way,
削弱演讲主题概念上的完整性
impairing the conceptual integrity of the theme.
是啊...
Yes...
我能先说点别的吗?
May I change the subject?
Jim 既然你来了 是否可以先向你
Jim, while you're here may I sound you out on a proposal
征求一下我打算给首相提的建议?
I was going to make to the Prime Minister?
什么建议?
What proposal?
这次政府的小变化给我们石油工业的
Our little change of Government has quite unnecessarily alarmed
一些投资者造成了不必要的恐慌
some of the investors in our oil industry.
当然只是暂时的 不过我们的确需要
Only temporarily of course, but it does mean that we need
一点英国投资帮我们渡过难关
a little British investment to tide us over.
来恢复信心 这你明白
To restore confidence, you know.
要多少?
How much?
五千万英镑
Fifty million pounds.
问问他还款期限
Ask him on what terms.
还款期限呢?
On what terms?
十年后开始偿还本金
Repayment of the capital not to start before ten years.
并且免利息
And interest free.
五千万英镑... 可是一笔巨款
Fifty million pounds... it's a lot of money.
我明白了 那样的话...
I see, well in that case...
但这并不意味我们不能谈谈? 嗨 Humphrey
But that doesn't mean we can't talk about it? Hey, Humphrey
免利息? 十年?
Interest free? Ten years?
假定利率是百分之十
Assuming that the interest would be a 10%
他要我们白白送给他五千万英镑
he's asking for a free gift of fifty million pounds.
这么看来你似乎是要
It would appear that you're rightly asking for
我们白送五千万英镑
is a free gift of about fifty million pounds.
但这对你们有利
But it's to your advantage.
我们会用贷款去买Clyde造的钻井
We would use the loan to buy oil rigs built on the Clyde.
这样...
Ah, well.
他要我们给他五千万英镑
He's asking us to give him 50 million pounds
然后用我们的钱买我们的钻井
so that he can buy our oil rigs with our money.
我觉得还算合理
Reasonable to me.
-合理 大臣?  -会创造很多工作 Humphrey
- Reasonable, Minister? - Lots of jobs, Humphrey.
Charlie 要是这笔交易做成了
Charlie, supposing it were possible to do this deal,
你是不是有可能会对
would you find it possible to make the
演讲内容做些必要的删减?
necessary cuts in your speech today?
是的 但现在就得定下来
Yes, but I'd have to know now.
真黑!(谐音Black male)
Blackmail!
你是在说我还是我的建议?
Are you describing me or my proposal?
当然是你的建议
Your proposal, naturally.
不 不 也不是你的建议
No, no, not even your proposal.
我想可以达成协议了 是吗 Humphrey?
I think we can come to agreement, don't you, Humphrey?
大臣...
Minister...
能和你说几句吗?
Could I have a word with you?
什么?
Yes?
请原谅 阁下
Will you excuse us, Your Excellency?
-有什么不妥吗?  -有什么妥当吗?
- Is anything wrong? - Is anything right?
他给了我们出路
He's offering us a way out.
出路? 要我们白送五千万 出路?
A way out? He's calling us to give a gift of 50mp. A way out?
-是贷款  -随你怎么说 这可永远也要不回来了
- It's a loan. - You call it what you like. We'll never get it back.
你打算花掉整整五千万公款
You're proposing to buy your way out of political involvement
来买条政治上的出路?
with fifty million pounds of public money?
-这就是外交  -这是腐败 大臣
- It's diplomacy. - It's corruption, Minister.
高级英帝国勋爵
K.B.E.
小汉
Humpy.
你的意思是...
You mean...
是的 我明白了
Yes, I see.
我想我们也不希望苏联人投资Buranda 是吧?
I suppose we don't want the Soviets to invest in Buranda, do we?
而且不可否认的是
And I suppose it could be argued that
我们应该负起责任来 尤其是对...
we have a responsibility to the...
非洲弹丸小国
T.P.L.A.C.'s.
是的 非常正确
Yes, quite.
好吧
Oh, good.
总统先生 我想我们可以达成协议了
Mr. President, I think we can come to terms after all.
-好吧 你知道我的价格  -你也知道我的
- Well, you know my price. - And you know mine.
人人都有个价格
Everyone has his price.
是 大臣
Yes, Minister.